<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><rss version="2.0"><channel><title>nix-book</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/</link><description>An mdBook-generated site</description><generator>mdbook-rss-feed 0.1.0</generator><item><title>index</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/index.html</link><description><![CDATA[]]></description><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/index.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 18:02:07 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Functions and NixOS Modules</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/functions/functions_and_modules_2.2.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>When you start exploring NixOS configurations or tools like Home Manager, you’ll
encounter a concept called Nix Modules. Modules are also functions, but they
behave differently regarding their arguments, which can be a source of
confusion.</p><p><strong>What are NixOS Modules</strong>?</p><p>Nix Modules are a powerful system built on top of basic Nix functions, primarily
used for declarative system configurations (like NixOS, Home Manager, NixOps,
etc.). They allow you to define parts of your system configuration in separate
files that are then composed together.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/functions/functions_and_modules_2.2.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>JJ VCS</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/vcs/jujutsu.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/jujutsu.png" alt="JJ Logo" /></p><p>⚠️ <strong>Security Reminder</strong>: Never commit secrets (passwords, API keys, tokens,
etc.) in plain text to your Git repository. If you plan to publish your NixOS
configuration, always use a secrets management tool like <code>sops-nix</code> or <code>agenix</code>
to keep sensitive data safe. See the
<a href="https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/sops-nix.html">Sops-Nix Guide</a>
for details.</p><p>Jujutsu (jj) is a modern, Git-compatible version control system designed to
simplify and improve the developer experience. It offers a new approach to
distributed version control, focusing on a more intuitive workflow, powerful
undo capabilities, and a branchless model that reduces common pitfalls of Git.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/vcs/jujutsu.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Git</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/vcs/git.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>⚠️ <strong>Important</strong>: Never commit secrets (passwords, API keys, tokens, etc.) in
plain text to your Git repository. If you plan to publish your NixOS
configuration, always use a secrets management tool like sops-nix or agenix to
keep sensitive data safe. See the
<a href="https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/sops-nix.html">Sops-Nix Guide</a>
for details.</p><p>It’s also important to understand that <strong>all files in the <code>/nix/store</code> are
world-readable by default</strong> This has important security implications for anyone
managing sensitive data on a NixOS system.</p><p>What Does “World-Readable” Mean?</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/vcs/git.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Flake Inputs</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/flake_inputs_4.1.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The attribute <code>inputs</code> specifies the dependencies of a flake, as an attrset
mapping input names to flake references.</p><p>If a repository provides a <code>flake.nix</code> you can include it as an input in your
<code>flake.nix</code>.</p><p>For example, I like yazi as my file explorer and have been using helix as my
editor. To be able to get yazi to work with helix I needed the latest versions
of both yazi and helix. One way to get the latest versions was to add their
flakes as inputs to my flake:</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/flake_inputs_4.1.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Understanding the Helix Flake</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/helix_flake_4.4.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/helix.png" alt="Helix Logo" />–<a href="https://helix-editor.com/">helix-editor.com</a></p><p>As we’ve seen from previous examples, the helix editor repository includes a few
<code>.nix</code> files including a <code>flake.nix</code>. Their flake uses a lot of idiomatic Nix
code and advanced features. First I will break down their <code>flake.nix</code> and
<code>default.nix</code> to understand why they do certain things. And finally, we will
change the build to “debug” mode demonstrating how easily you can modify the
behavior of a package defined within a Nix flake without changing the original
source code or the upstream flake directly.</p><pre><code class="language-bash">git clone https://github.com/helix-editor/helix.git
cd helix
</code></pre>
<p>When you enter ]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/helix_flake_4.4.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Flake outputs</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/flake_examples_4.3.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>This chapter provides practical examples to illustrate the concepts discussed in
“Nix Flakes Explained.”</p><p>NixOS modules and configurations offer us a powerful and composable way to
define and share system configurations. Imagine we have several independent
“players,” each with their own unique set of configurations or modules. How do
we combine these individual contributions into a single, cohesive system without
directly altering each player’s original flake?</p><p>This example demonstrates how flakes can extend and compose each other, allowing
you to layer configurations on top of existing ones. This is particularly useful
when you want to:</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/flake_examples_4.3.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Flake outputs</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/flake_outputs_4.2.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Flake outputs are what the flake produces when built. Flakes can have multiple
outputs simultaneously such as:</p><p><strong>Packages</strong>: Self-contained bundles that are built using derivations and
provide either some kind of software or dependencies of software.</p><p><a href="https://saylesss88.github.io/NixOS_Modules_Explained_3.html">NixOS modules</a></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/flake_outputs_4.2.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nix Pull Requests</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Nix_Pull_Requests_11.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/gruv16.png" alt="gruv16" /></p><p><strong>Pull requests</strong> communicate changes to a branch in a repository. Once a pull
request is opened, you can review changes with collaborators and add follow-up
commits.</p><p>A <strong>pull request</strong> is a proposal to merge a set of changes from one branch
into another. In a pull request, collaborators can review and discuss the
proposed set of changes before they integrate the changes into the main
codebase.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Nix_Pull_Requests_11.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 27 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Unencrypted BTRFS Impermanence with Flakes</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/unenc/unenc_impermanence.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Figure 1: Impermanence Logo: Image of the Impermanence logo. Sourced from the</p><p><a href="https://github.com/nix-community/impermanence">Impermanence repo</a></p><p>This guide is for an unencrypted setup, there are a few links at the end for
encrypted setups. This guide follows the previous
<a href="https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/unencrypted_setups.html">minimal install guide</a>
but you should be able to adjust it carefully to meet your needs.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/unenc/unenc_impermanence.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 24 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Debugging NixOS modules</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Debugging_and_Tracing_NixOS_Modules_9.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>This chapter covers debugging NixOS modules, focusing on tracing module options
and evaluating merges.</p><p><img src="images/coding4.png" alt="404" /></p><p><a href="https://saylesss88.github.io/posts/nix_modules_explained/">nix-modules-explained</a></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Debugging_and_Tracing_NixOS_Modules_9.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>NixOS Containers</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nixos_containers.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/boxes.cleaned.png" alt="boxes" /></p><p>NixOS containers are lightweight <code>systemd-nspawn</code> containers managed
declaratively through your NixOS configuration. They allow you to run separate,
minimal NixOS instances on the same machine, each with its own services,
packages, and (optionally) network stack.</p><p>❗ NixOS’ containers do not provide full security out of the box (just like
docker). They do give you a separate chroot, but a privileged user (root) in a
container can escape the container and become root on the host system.
–<a href="https://blog.beardhatcode.be/2020/12/Declarative-Nixos-Containers.html">beardhatcode Declarative-Nixos-Containers</a></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nixos_containers.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Practical Nix Functions</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/functions/practical_functions_2.1.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/coding6.png" alt="coding6" /></p><p><a href="https://gitlab.com/api/v4/projects/4207231/packages/generic/graphviz-releases/2.49.3/graphviz-2.49.3.tar.gz">graphviz</a></p><p><a href="https://ftp.gnu.org/gnu/hello/hello-2.12.1.tar.gz">hello</a></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/functions/practical_functions_2.1.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Overlays</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/overlays_4.5.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/pokego.png" alt="Pokego Logo" />–<a href="https://github.com/rubiin/pokego">pokego repo</a></p><p>Overlays are Nix functions that accept two arguments, <code>final</code> and <code>prev</code> and
return a set of packages. Overlays are similar to <code>packageOverrides</code> as a way to
customize Nixpkgs, <code>packageOverrides</code> acts as an overlay with only the <code>prev</code>
argument. Therefore, <code>packageOverrides</code> is appropriate for basic use, but
overlays are more powerful and easier to distribute.</p><p>Example:</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/overlays_4.5.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Specialisations</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/specialisations_4.6.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><strong>NixOS specialisations</strong> are a powerful feature that allow you to define
alternative system configurations variations within a single NixOS setup. Each
specialisation can modify or extend the base configuration, and NixOS will
generate separate boot entries for each, letting you choose at boot time (or
switch at runtime) which environment to use. This is ideal for testing,
hardware-specific tweaks, or separating work and personal environments without
maintaining multiple configuration files</p><p>Specialisations are defined as attributes under the <code>specialisation</code> option in
your configuration. Each key (e.g., <code>niri-test</code>) represents a named
specialisation, and its configuration attribute contains the NixOS options to
apply on top of the base system</p]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/flakes/specialisations_4.6.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Comparing Flakes and Traditional Nix</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Comparing_Flakes_and_Traditional_Nix_8.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>A key benefit of Nix Flakes is their <em>default</em> enforcement of <strong>pure
evaluation</strong>.</p><p>In Nix, an <strong>impure operation</strong> depends on something <em>outside</em> its explicit
inputs. Examples include:</p><p>Impurity leads to unpredictable builds that may differ across systems or time.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Comparing_Flakes_and_Traditional_Nix_8.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hardening Networking</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/hardening_networking.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Since networks and systems vary, some adjustments may cause unexpected issues,
especially around critical components like DNS or firewalls. Always review and
test changes in a controlled environment before applying them broadly.</p><p>Understand the trade-offs and tailor the settings to your threat model and
workflow. Take what’s useful, adapt as needed, and seek expert guidance for
more advanced scenarios.</p><p>Every setup is unique, feel free to adapt or skip sections based on your needs.
Start with the basics and build up as you gain confidence. The goal is
practical, tested hardening tailored to you.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/hardening_networking.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sops-Nix</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/sops-nix.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/getsops/sops?ref=blog.gitguardian.com">SOPS</a>, short for
<strong>S</strong>ecrets<strong>OP</strong>eration<strong>S</strong>, is an editor of encrypted files that supports
quite a few BINARY formats and encrypts with AWS KMS, GCP KMS, Azure Key Vault,
age, and PGP.</p><p>Managing secrets—like API keys, SSH deploy keys, and password hashes is a
critical part of system configuration, but it’s also one of the trickiest to do
securely and reproducibly. Traditionally, secrets might be stored in ad hoc
locations, referenced by absolute paths, or managed manually outside of version
control. This approach makes it hard to share, rebuild, or audit your
configuration, and increases the risk of accidental leaks or inconsistencies
between systems.</p><p><code>sops-nix]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/sops-nix.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Encrypted Impermanence</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/encrypted_impermanence.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>❗ Important Note: This guide details a setup involving encrypted partitions
and impermanent NixOS. While powerful, such configurations require careful
attention to detail. Incorrect steps, especially concerning encryption keys or
persistent data paths, can lead to <strong>permanent data loss</strong>. Please read all
instructions thoroughly before proceeding and consider backing up any critical
data beforehand. This has only been tested with the disk layout described in
<a href="https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/encrypted_manual.html">Encrypted Setups</a></p><pre><code class="language-nix"># flake.nix
{
  description = "NixOS configuration";

  inputs = {
    nixpkgs.url = "github:nixos/nixpkgs/nixos-unstable";
    disko.url = "github:nix-community/disko/latest";
    disko.input]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/encrypted_impermanence.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Hardening NixOS</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/hardening_NixOS.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/guy_fawks.png" alt="guy fawks hacker" /></p><p>Securing your NixOS system begins with a philosophy of minimalism, explicit
configuration, and proactive control. As desktop Linux attracts more novice
users, it has become an increasingly valuable target for attackers. This makes
it crucial to adopt security best practices early to protect your desktop from
common attack vectors and to avoid configuration mistakes that could expose
vulnerabilities.</p><p>⚠️ Warning: I am not a security expert. This guide presents various options
for hardening NixOS, but it is your responsibility to evaluate whether each
adjustment suits your specific needs and environment. Security hardening and
process isolation can introduce stability challenges, compatibility issues, or
unexpected be]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/hardening_NixOS.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Whonix KVM on NixOS</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/whonix_kvm.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="../images/swappy-20250901-101339.cleaned.png" alt="Whonix Logo" /></p><p>⚠️ WARNING: There is no general software that can guarantee absolute anonymity
or security; perfect security is a myth. Security is a continuous process, not
a one-time product. It also depends on time and resources: if an adversary has
enough of either, eventual compromise is probable. However, by layering
defenses and following best practices, we can make attacks costly and
time-consuming, deterring all but highly targeted adversaries.</p><p>It is highly recommended to harden your Host Machine as Type 2 hypervisors are
only as secure as their host. KVM is actually a type 1 hypervisor but relies on
QEMU for emulation which is a Type 2 hypervisor. This actually makes it a sort
of hybrid in between Type 1 ]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/whonix_kvm.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Unencrypted Impermanence</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/impermanence.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Figure 1: <strong>Impermanence Logo</strong>: Image of the Impermanence logo. Sourced from
the</p><p><a href="https://github.com/nix-community/impermanence">Impermanence repo</a></p><p><img src="../images/Impermanence.png" alt="Impermanence Logo" /></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/impermanence.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Cachix devour-flake</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/cachix_devour.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Using devour-flake to Cache All Your Flake Outputs to Cachix</p><p>When working with Nix flakes, it’s common to have many outputs—packages, apps,
dev shells, NixOS or Darwin configurations, and more. Efficiently building and
caching all these outputs can be challenging, especially in CI or when
collaborating. This is where devour-flake and Cachix shine. Why Use
devour-flake?</p><p>By default, building all outputs of a flake with <code>nix build .#a .#b ... .#z</code> can
be slow and inefficient, as Nix will evaluate the flake multiple times—once for
each output. devour-flake solves this by generating a “consumer” flake that
depends on all outputs, allowing you to build everything in one go with a single
evaluation</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/cachix_devour.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Readme1</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/index.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>📌 <strong>How to Use This Guide</strong></p><p><strong>Read warnings</strong>: Advanced hardening can break compatibility or cause data
loss! Pause and research before enabling anything not listed above unless you
understand the consequences.</p><p>The guide is broken up into 2 chapters:</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/index.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>GnuPG gpg-agent</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/gpg-agent.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>⚠️ <strong>SECURITY WARNING</strong>: This guide involves sensitive cryptographic material.
<strong>Never share your private key or passphrase</strong>. Backup your keys and handle
them with extreme care.</p><p><strong>GnuPG</strong> is a complete and free implementation of the OpenPGP standard. It
allows you to encrypt and sign your data and communications, has a versatile key
management system, and access modules for many kinds of public key directories.
GnuPG (GPG), is a command line tool for secure communication.</p><p><strong>PGP (Pretty Good Privacy)</strong> and <strong>GPG (GNU Privacy Guard)</strong>. While distinct,
they are deeply interconnected and, for the rest of this section, I’ll use the
terms interchangeably.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/gpg-agent.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nix Paths</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/nixLang/nix_paths.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The following examples are done with a local <code>nixpkgs</code> clone located at
<code>~/src/nixpkgs</code></p><p>Paths in Nix always need a <code>/</code> in them and always expand to absolute paths
relative to your current directory.</p><pre><code class="language-bash">nix repl
nix-repl&gt; ./.
/home/jr/src/nixpkgs
nix-repl&gt; ./. + "/lib"
/home/jr/src/nixpkgs/lib
</code></pre>
<p>Nix does <em>path normalization</em> every time you append strings, so if you just add
a slash <code>/</code> its not actually there:</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/nixLang/nix_paths.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nix Package Manager</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/nix_package_manager.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Nix is a <em>purely functional package manager</em>. This means that it treats packages
like values in purely functional programming languages – they are built by
functions that don’t have side-effects, and they never change after they have
been built.</p><p>Nix stores packages in the <em>Nix store</em>, usually the directory <code>/nix/store</code>,
where each package has its own unique subdirectory such as:</p><pre><code class="language-bash">/nix/store/y53c0lamag5wpx7vsiv7wmnjdgq97yd6-yazi-25.5.14pre20250526_74a8ea9
</code></pre>
<p>You can use the Nix on most Linux distributions and Mac OS also has good support
for Nix. It should work on most platforms that support POSIX threads and have a
C++11 compiler.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/nix_package_manager.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>KVM</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/kvm.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/steampunk5.cleaned.png" alt="sp5" /></p><p><strong>Host</strong> <code>secureblue</code> = Fedora Atomic with <strong>SELinux enforcing</strong>, <strong>sVirt</strong>,
<strong>Secure Boot</strong>, and hardened defaults.</p><p><strong>Guest</strong>: NixOS in a VM → full declarative power, near zero risk to host.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/kvm.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nix Lang</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/nix_language.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The Nix language is designed for conveniently creating and composing
<em>derivations</em> precise descriptions of how contents of files are used to derive
new files. –<a href="https://nix.dev/manual/nix/2.28/language/">Nix Reference Manual</a></p><p>Nix is often described as “JSON with functions.” It’s a declarative language
where you define outcomes, not step-by-step instructions. Instead of writing
sequential code, you create expressions that describe data structures,
functions, and dependencies. These expressions are evaluated lazily, meaning Nix
computes values only when needed, making it efficient for managing large
systems.</p><p>You can plug most of the following into the <code>nix repl</code> I’m showing it in a
single code block here for brevity:</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nix/nix_language.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>My Chapter</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/index.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>This section provides detailed guides for installing NixOS. You’ll choose
between an <strong>unencrypted</strong> or <strong>encrypted</strong> base setup. After your core
installation, you can explore adding optional features like <code>sops</code> for encrypted
secrets, <code>lanzaboote</code> for Secure Boot, or <code>impermanence</code> for a stateless system.</p><p><strong>Guide:</strong>
<a href="https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/unencrypted/unencrypted.html">Minimal Btrfs-Subvol Install with Disko and Flakes</a></p><p><strong>Best for:</strong></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/index.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>USB Keyfile</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/USB_keyfile.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>This allows you to use a USB stick for your keyfile, with a backup in case you
want or need it. There is a setting <code>fallbackToPassword</code> that protects you in
case something fails with the USB key.</p><p>First, I’ll show how to set up a dedicated USB stick for a keyfile. (i.e., one
that is only used for this). After that I will show the process of adding the
keyfile to a USB stick with existing data on it that you don’t want to lose.</p><p><strong>Generate the keyfile</strong></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/USB_keyfile.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Sops-Nix</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/sops-nix.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/getsops/sops?ref=blog.gitguardian.com">SOPS</a>, short for
<strong>S</strong>ecrets<strong>OP</strong>eration<strong>S</strong>, is an editor of encrypted files that supports
quite a few BINARY formats and encrypts with AWS KMS, GCP KMS, Azure Key Vault,
age, and PGP.</p><p>Managing secrets—like API keys, SSH deploy keys, and password hashes is a
critical part of system configuration, but it’s also one of the trickiest to do
securely and reproducibly. Traditionally, secrets might be stored in ad hoc
locations, referenced by absolute paths, or managed manually outside of version
control. This approach makes it hard to share, rebuild, or audit your
configuration, and increases the risk of accidental leaks or inconsistencies
between systems.</p><p><code>sops-nix]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/sops-nix.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Encrypted Install</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/enc_install.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>NixOS supports file systems that are encrypted using LUKS (Linux Unified Key
Setup). This guide walks you through an encrypted NixOS installation using Disko
for disk management and Btrfs for subvolumes. It is designed for users who want
full disk encryption and a modern filesystem layout. If you prefer an
unencrypted setup, you can skip the LUKS and encryption steps, but this guide
focuses on security and flexibility.</p><p>If you choose to set up impermanence, ensure it matches your install. Encrypted
Setup with Encrypted Impermanence and Unencrypted Setup with Unencrypted
Impermanence.</p><p>❗ NOTE: This is a bit convoluted, there are a few paths you can follow. If
you choose to use the starter repo (<a href="https://github.com/saylesss88/my-flake">https://github.com/saylesss88/my-fl]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/enc_install.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Encrypted Impermanence</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/encrypted_impermanence.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>❗ Important Note: This guide details a setup involving encrypted partitions
and impermanent NixOS. While powerful, such configurations require careful
attention to detail. Incorrect steps, especially concerning encryption keys or
persistent data paths, can lead to <strong>permanent data loss</strong>. Please read all
instructions thoroughly before proceeding and consider backing up any critical
data beforehand. This has only been tested with the disk layout described in
<a href="https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/encrypted_manual.html">Encrypted Setups</a></p><p>As a system operates, it gradually accumulates state on its root partition. This
state is stored in various directories such as <code>/etc</code> and <code>/var</code>, capturing all
the configuration changes, logs, and o]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/encrypted_impermanence.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Lanzaboote</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/lanzaboote.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>⚠️ <strong>Warning: This can easily brick your system</strong> ⚠️</p><p>We will mainly follow the lanzaboote
<a href="https://github.com/nix-community/lanzaboote/blob/master/docs/QUICK_START.md">Quick Start Guide</a></p><p>For Windows dual-booters and BitLocker users, you should export your BitLocker
recovery keys and confirm that they are correct. Refer to this
<a href="https://support.microsoft.com/en-us/windows/find-your-bitlocker-recovery-key-6b71ad27-0b89-ea08-f143-056f5ab347d6">Microsoft support article</a></p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/enc/lanzaboote.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Unencrypted Install</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/unenc/unencrypted_setups.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>Figure 1: BTRFS Logo: Image of the BTRFS logo. Sourced from the BTRFS repo BTRFS
logo</p><p>Why I Chose BTRFS I chose BTRFS because I was already familiar with it from
using it with Arch Linux and I found it to be very easy to use. From what I’ve
read, there are licensing issues between the Linux Kernel and ZFS which means
that ZFS is not part of the Linux Kernel; it’s maintained by the OpenZFS project
and available as a separate kernel module. This can cause issues and make you
think more about your filesystem than I personally want to at this point.</p><p>A <strong>Btrfs subvolume</strong> is essentially a distinct section within a Btrfs
filesystem that maintains its own set of files and directories, along with a
separate inode numbering system. Unlike block-level partitions (such as ]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/installation/unenc/unencrypted_setups.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Local Nixpkgs</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nixpkgs/local_package.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>This chapter demonstrates the fundamental pattern for creating a package. Every
package recipe is a file that declares a function. This function takes the
packages dependencies as argument.</p><p>In this example we’ll make a simple package with <code>coreutils</code> and build it.
Demonstrating the process of building and testing a local package.</p><p>This chapter will assume you have already have a cloned fork of Nixpkgs. I
choose to clone mine to the <code>~/src/</code> directory.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nixpkgs/local_package.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Fork, Clone, Contribute</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nixpkgs/fork_clone_contribute.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>In the <a href="https://github.com/NixOS/nixpkgs">Nixpkgs</a> Repository.</p><p>Click Fork, then Create a new Fork.</p><p>Uncheck the box “Only fork the <code>master</code> branch”, for development we will need
more branches.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nixpkgs/fork_clone_contribute.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nixpkgs Overlays</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/nixpkgs/overlay.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>The following is done with a local clone of Nixpkgs located at <code>~/src/nixpkgs</code>.</p><p>In this example, we will create an overlay to override the version of
<code>btrfs-progs</code>. In the root directory of our local clone of Nixpkgs
(i.e.<code>~/src/nixpkgs</code>) we can run the following command to locate <code>btrfs-progs</code>
within Nixpkgs:</p><pre><code class="language-bash">fd 'btrfs-progs' .
./pkgs/by-name/bt/btrfs-progs/
</code></pre>
<p>Open the <code>package.nix</code> in the above directory and copy the <code>src</code> block within
the <code>stdenv.mkDerivation</code> block like so:</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/nixpkgs/overlay.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Local Nixpkgs</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Working_with_Nixpkgs_Locally_10.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/server_rack.cleaned.png" alt="server_rack" /></p><p>Nixpkgs, the package repository for NixOS, is a powerful resource for building
and customizing software.</p><p>Working with a local copy enhances development, debugging, and contribution
workflows.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Working_with_Nixpkgs_Locally_10.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Intro to Nushell</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/intro_to_nushell_on_NixOS.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/nu.png" alt="Nu" /></p><p><strong>TL;DR</strong>:I recently switched default shells from zsh to nushell, this post is
about some of the challenges and advantages of using nushell with NixOS.</p><p>While the average user might not immediately see significant advantages, those
who frequently work with structured data formats like JSON, YAML, and CSV –
such as developers interacting with APIs, system administrators managing
configurations, and data professionals – will likely find Nushell’s native
data handling and powerful pipeline capabilities a plus. Additionally, users
who value a more consistent and safer scripting experience might appreciate
Nushell’s language-first design and features like strong typing.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/intro_to_nushell_on_NixOS.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Package Definitions Explained</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Package_Definitions_Explained_6.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/coding2.png" alt="coding2" /></p><p>In Nix, the concept of a <strong>package</strong> can refer to two things:</p><p>A collection of files and data that constitute a piece of software or an
artifact.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Package_Definitions_Explained_6.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Top-Level Attributes</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Understanding_Top-Level_Attributes_5.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p>This explanation is based on insights from Infinisil, a prominent figure in the
Nix community, to help clarify the concept of top-level attributes within NixOS
modules.</p><p>In a NixOS system, everything is built from a single “system derivation.” The
command <code>nix-build '&lt;nixpkgs/nixos&gt;' -A system</code> initiates this build process.</p><p>The <code>-A system</code> part tells Nix to focus on the <code>system</code> attribute defined in the
<code>'&lt;nixpkgs/nixos&gt;'</code> file (which is essentially <code>./default.nix</code> within the
Nixpkgs repository).</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Understanding_Top-Level_Attributes_5.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Intro to Nix</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Getting_Started_with_Nix_1.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/trees1.cleaned.png" alt="trees" /></p><p>Welcome to <em>nix-book</em>, an introductory book about Nix. This book leans more
towards using Flakes but will contrast traditional Nix where beneficial.
Originally, this content started as a blog. I’m refining its flow to make it
more cohesive.</p><p>In this chapter, I will touch on the different parts of the Nix ecosystem, give
a quick example of each and explain how they fit together.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Getting_Started_with_Nix_1.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nix Flakes Explained</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Nix_Flakes_Explained_4.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/trees3.cleaned.png" alt="trees3" /></p><p>If you’re completely new, take a look at
<a href="https://nixos.wiki/wiki/flakes#Installing_flakes">this</a> to get flakes on your
system.</p><p>For the Nix Flake man page type <code>man nix3 flake</code> and for a specific feature,
type something like <code>man nix3 flake-lock</code>.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Nix_Flakes_Explained_4.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Nix Module System Explained</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/NixOS_Modules_Explained_3.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/buildings1.png" alt="buildings" /></p><p><strong>TL;DR</strong>: In this chapter, we will break down the Nix module system used by
both NixOS and Home-Manager. We will discuss using home-manager as a module and
the flexibility that modules give us. We will touch on options and break down
the <code>vim</code> module from the Nixpkgs collection. Finally we will display how to
test modules with the repl.</p><p>Your <code>configuration.nix</code> is a module. For the Nixpkgs collection most modules
are in <code>nixos/modules</code>.</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/NixOS_Modules_Explained_3.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Understanding Nix Functions</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Understanding_Nix_Functions_2.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/trees2.cleaned.png" alt="trees2" /></p><p><strong>Functions</strong> are the building blocks of Nix, appearing everywhere in Nix
expressions and configurations. Mastering them is essential for writing
effective Nix code and understanding tools like NixOS and Home Manager. This
chapter explores how Nix functions work, focusing on their <strong>single-argument
nature</strong>, <strong>currying</strong>, <strong>partial application</strong>, and their role in <strong>modules</strong>.</p><p>A <strong>Nix Function</strong> is a rule that takes an input (called an <strong>argument</strong>) and
produces an <strong>output</strong> based on that input. Unlike many programming languages,
Nix functions are designed to take exactly one argument at a time. This unique
approach, co]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Understanding_Nix_Functions_2.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item><item><title>Intro to Derivations</title><link>https://saylesss88.github.io/Intro_to_Nix_Derivations_7.html</link><description><![CDATA[<p><img src="images/gruv10.png" alt="gruv10" /></p><p>Nix’s build instructions, known as <strong>derivations</strong>, are defined using the Nix
Language. These derivations can describe anything from individual software
packages to complete system configurations. The Nix package manager then
deterministically “realizes” (builds) these derivations, ensuring consistency
because they rely solely on a predefined set of inputs.</p><p>Most things in NixOS are built around derivations. Your NixOS system is
described by such a single system derivation. When you want to apply a new
configuration, <code>nixos-rebuild</code> handles the process:</p>]]></description><author>saylesss88</author><guid>https://saylesss88.github.io/Intro_to_Nix_Derivations_7.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 21 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate></item></channel></rss>